<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead>
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" repositoryencoding="iso15511" dateencoding="iso8601" relatedencoding="Dublin Core" scriptencoding="iso15924" countryencoding="iso3166-1">
    <eadid countrycode="us" mainagencycode="MiU-H" publicid="us//::miu-h//TXT us::miu-h::bethisraelcong.xml//EN" encodinganalog="Identifier"> umich-bhl-2013047</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper encodinganalog="Title">Finding Aid for Beth Israel Congregation Jewish Life in Ann Arbor Oral History Project records </titleproper>
        <author encodinganalog="Creator">Collection processed and finding aid created by Robert Goldey </author>
      </titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher encodinganalog="Publisher">Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan</publisher>
        <date encodinganalog="Date" normal="2015"> 2015</date>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Encoded finding aid created by Olga Virakhovskaya <date>2015</date></creation>
      <langusage encodinganalog="Language">The finding aid is written in <language langcode="eng" scriptcode="Latn">English</language></langusage>
      <descrules>Finding aid prepared using Describing Archives: A Content Standard (DACS)</descrules>
    </profiledesc>
    <revisiondesc>
      <change>
        <date>2015-09-22</date>
        <item>Original encoding from Word 10.0 file using Word macros and Xmetal.</item>
      </change>
    </revisiondesc>
    <classification ref="/repositories/2/classifications/1"/>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <publisher>Michigan Historical Collections <lb/>Bentley Historical Library <lb/>University of Michigan</publisher>
      <titleproper>Finding aid for<lb/> Beth Israel Congregation Jewish Life in Ann Arbor Oral History Project Records</titleproper>
      <author>Finding aid created by<lb/> Robert Goldey, in October 2013 </author>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="recordgrp" audience="external" type="inventory" relatedencoding="MARC21">
    <did>
      <origination>
        <corpname source="lcnaf" encodinganalog="110" ref="/agents/corporate_entities/21327">Beth Israel Congregation (Ann Arbor, Mich.)</corpname>
      </origination>
      <unittitle encodinganalog="245"> Beth Israel Congregation Jewish Life in Ann Arbor Oral History Project records</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" encodinganalog="245$f"> 2013 </unitdate><physdesc altrender="part">
        <extent altrender="materialtype spaceoccupied">0.2 linear feet</extent>
      </physdesc>
      <physdesc altrender="part">
        <extent altrender="materialtype spaceoccupied">7.48 GB</extent>
        <physfacet>online</physfacet>
      </physdesc>
      <unitid encodinganalog="852$h" repositorycode="miu-h" countrycode="us" type="call number"> 2013047 Aa 2 </unitid>
      <langmaterial>The material is in <language langcode="eng" encodinganalog="041">English</language></langmaterial>
      <abstract> Ann Arbor Congregation founded in 1916. In anticipation of its 100th anniversary in 2016, Beth Israel initiated an oral history project to help tell the story of Jewish life in Ann Arbor, Michigan. Recordings were conducted in April 2013 by StoryCorps, a national non-profit organization dedicated to recording and collecting stories of everyday people. Includes digital recordings of interviews, transcripts, and digital photographs of participants. </abstract>
      <repository>
        <corpname encodinganalog="852"><subarea>Bentley Historical Library</subarea>, University of Michigan</corpname>
        <extptr href="bhladd" show="embed" actuate="onload"/>
      </repository>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admin">
      <acqinfo encodinganalog="541">
        <p>Materials were donated by the Beth Israel Congregation of Ann Arbor, Mich. (donor no. <num type="donor" encodinganalog="541$e">6312</num>) in 2013. </p>
      </acqinfo>
      <accruals encodinganalog="584">
        <p>Periodic additions to the records expected.</p>
      </accruals>
      <accessrestrict encodinganalog="506">
        <p>The collection is open without restriction. Access is available from the Bentley Historical Library's Reading Room only.</p>
        <p>
          <extptr href="uarpacc" show="embed" actuate="onload"/>
        </p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict encodinganalog="540">
        <p> Copyright is held by StoryCorps, Inc., 80 Hanson Place, Brooklyn, NY 11217. </p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite encodinganalog="524">
        <p>[item], folder, box, Beth Israel Congregation Jewish Life in Ann Arbor Oral History Project Records, Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan</p>
      </prefercite>
      <processinfo>
        <p>
          <extptr href="digitalproc" show="embed" actuate="onload"/>
        </p>
      </processinfo>
    </descgrp>
    <bioghist encodinganalog="545">
      <p>As in many Midwestern towns, the first Jewish residents of Ann Arbor, Michigan were Central European immigrants, usually peddlers, who began to settle down in the 1840s. Solomon Weil, a peddler and native of Bohemia, came to Ann Arbor in 1845. By the mid-1850s, he and his four brothers had established the firm of J. Weil and Brothers, tanners and dealers in wool and furs. The primary remnant of this early Jewish community is a cemetery--the first Jewish burial ground in Michigan--that is located at the corner of Huron and Fletcher streets on the current University of Michigan campus. (The appearance in 1980 of a tombstone dated 1858 led to the discovery of the Jewish cemetery.) By the mid-1880s, the last Jewish family of this early settlement had left town. </p>
      <p>The great wave of Jewish migration from Eastern Europe (1870-1914) created a new Jewish community in Ann Arbor. Early Jewish residents included the Brodys and Schultzes, who operated a grocery store in Ypsilanti from the 1890s and the Lanskys, who started a scrap metal business in 1904. In the 1910s, the community began to grow, including several persons who would play critical roles in the emergence of the first communal institutions. In 1913 Osias and Hannah Zwerdling held High Holiday services in their home. This gathering grew to become Beth Israel Congregation, founded in 1916. Zwerdling, a furrier, served as president of the synagogue from 1918 to 1958. The congregation survived in a series of rented rooms before it moved to a new University of Michigan B'nai Brith Hillel building in 1951. The congregation moved to its own building in 1978. It is affiliated with the Conservative movement of Judaism. As the Jewish population grew, with increasing numbers of Jewish faculty and students at the university, the Jewish communal institutions began to diversify. In 1966, a group of Jews sympathetic to Reform Judaism formed the nucleus of what became Temple Beth Emeth. In an unusual arrangement, the temple jointly owns and shares a building with St. Clare's Episcopal Church, through an umbrella organization known as Genesis. Around the same time, a more secular-oriented group established the Jewish Cultural Society. An Orthodox "minyan" emerged in the early 1970s, initially under the auspices of the University of Michigan Hillel Foundation. The Hebrew Day School, which provides Jewish and secular education for elementary age children, was founded in 1975. Chabad House was organized the same year. In 1984 a group began meeting to organize a Jewish Community Center, which began operation in a building at 2300 E. Stadium Blvd. that year. In 1986 the Jewish Community Center purchased a former public school--Clinton School--to house the center's expanding programs as well as the Hebrew Day School and the Jewish Cultural Society. The Ann Arbor Reconstructionist Congregation, which was formally organized in 1994, began as a<title render="italic"> Havurah</title>, an informal group of families who gathered to celebrate Shabbat and other holidays. In 2015, the congregation, which meets at the Jewish Community Center, had a rabbi and a religious school. Jewish Family Services, which grew from efforts to resettle Jews from the Soviet Union in the late 1970s, was founded in 1993.</p>
      <p>What is today known as the Jewish Federation of Greater Ann Arbor began in 1961 as the United Jewish Appeal of Washtenaw County. Its primary purpose was to raise funds for Israel and other overseas needs. In the 1960s, the United Jewish Appeal raised about $30,000, all of which went overseas. In 1982, the annual campaign raised $303,000, of which 77 percent went overseas. In keeping with national trends, as the Ann Arbor Jewish community grew, the percentage of funds allocated locally began to grow. In the 2014 annual campaign, 78.6 percent ($1,105,433) of the $1,405,000 collected went to strengthen local Jewish organizations, while the remaining $334,567 was allocated to "Global Giving."</p>
      <p>The increasing size of annual campaigns and the dramatic shift in funding allocations reflected the increased size and vitality of the Ann Arbor Jewish community. In postwar America, Jews began to enter the academy and the professions. American higher education, including the University of Michigan, entered a period of explosive growth. Jews became a greater presence in the faculty, as anti-Semitic attitudes declined, and the student body, which had always attracted a certain number of East Coast Jews, drew increasing numbers of Jewish students. All of this led to a dramatic increase in the Jewish population of Washtenaw County, which is estimated at 8,000 in 2015. The Jewish student population at the University of Michigan is estimated at an additional 6,000.</p>
      <p>Celebrating Our Stories: Jewish Life in Ann Arbor</p>
      <p>As part of a celebration of the congregation's 100th year anniversary, Beth Israel received a grant to fund "Celebrating Our Stories: Jewish Life in Ann Arbor," from the Jewish Federation of Greater Ann Arbor's Community Impact Award Fund in December of 2011. The grant allowed Beth Israel to bring StoryCorps to the congregation to record oral histories with members of the Jewish community in April 2013. In December of 2012, the project received additional funding from the Community Impact Fund to enable web access of these recordings and other historical material relevant to Beth Israel and the greater Jewish community.</p>
      <p>StoryCorps is a non-profit organization dedicated to recording, preserving, and sharing the stories of Americans of all backgrounds. The organization is modeled after the efforts of the Depression-era Works Progress Administration to collect oral histories across the country. StoryCorps is one of the largest oral history projects of its kind and launched the first National Day of Listening in 2008 with the goal of encouraging all Americans to record an interview with a loved one.</p>
      <p>The format of StoryCorps interviews centers around two or three individuals who are familiar with each other such as friends or family and have a conversation on a predetermined topic. A trained StoryCorps representative records and facilitates the conversation, takes pictures, and organizes the accompanying documents. Each conversation typically lasts about 40 minutes. The storytellers are then given a CD of their conversation and, with the participant's permission, the interview is archived at the American Folklife Center at the Library of Congress and various community archives across the United States.</p>
      <p>Sources:</p>
      <p>Ann Arbor in www.jewishvirtuallibrary.org</p>
      <p>Endelman, Todd M. <title render="italic">A Short History of the Jews of the Ann Arbor Area.</title> Ann Arbor: Jewish Federation of Washtenaw County/United Jewish Appeal, 1997.</p>
      <p>Beth Israel Congregation: http://www.bethisrael-aa.org/</p>
      <p>StoryCorps: http://storycorps.org/</p>
    </bioghist>
    <arrangement encodinganalog="351">
      <p> The collection has been arranged into two series: Interviews and Printed Transcripts.</p>
    </arrangement>
    <scopecontent encodinganalog="520">
      <p>The Beth Israel oral history project records consist of 18 interviews of congregation members that were facilitated and recorded by StoryCorps, a national non-profit organization dedicated to recording and collecting stories of everyday people. The interview participants were of a range of ages and experiences with subject matter centered on their experience of Jewish life in Ann Arbor. Common themes ranged from their life stories, their participation in Ann Arbor Jewish life, how they became involved in Jewish communal life, discussions of their Jewish identity, and any anti-Semitism they encountered. </p>
    </scopecontent>
    <controlaccess>
      <p>
        <extptr href="accnote" show="embed" actuate="onload"/>
      </p>
      <controlaccess>
        <head>Subjects:</head>
        <geogname source="lcsh" encodinganalog="651" ref="/subjects/1297">Ann Arbor (Mich.)--Religion.</geogname>
        <corpname source="lcnaf" encodinganalog="610" ref="/agents/corporate_entities/21327">Beth Israel Congregation (Ann Arbor, Mich.)</corpname>
        <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650" ref="/subjects/6321">Conservative Judaism--Michigan--Ann Arbor.</subject>
        <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650" ref="/subjects/6322">Jews--History.</subject>
        <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650" ref="/subjects/6319">Jews--Michigan--Ann Arbor.</subject>
        <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650" ref="/subjects/6323">Jews--Religion--Michigan--Ann Arbor.</subject>
        <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650" ref="/subjects/6324">Jews--Social life and customs--Michigan--Ann Arbor.</subject>
        <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650" ref="/subjects/6320">Synagogues--Michigan--Ann Arbor.</subject>
      </controlaccess>
      <controlaccess>
        <head>Genre Terms:</head>
        <genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655" ref="/subjects/3189">Digital file formats.</genreform>
        <genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655" ref="/subjects/3190">Interviews.</genreform>
        <genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655" ref="/subjects/3191">Oral histories (document genres).</genreform>
        <genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655" ref="/subjects/3139">Sound recordings.</genreform>
        <genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655" ref="/subjects/3192">Transcripts.</genreform>
      </controlaccess>
    </controlaccess>
    <dsc type="combined">
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Interviews</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>The Interviews series (7.47 GB online) includes full materials from recording sessions conducted by StoryCorps. Each interview consists of a 45 minute sound recording, a transcript (produced by members of Beth Israel), log files that document key points in the conversation and corresponding time stamps, and photographs of the storytellers and interviewers. Every interview was conducted in a group of two to three people with some level of familiarity with each other, recorded by StoryCorps, who processed and compiled all materials accept for the aforementioned transcripts. </p>
        </scopecontent>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <physloc>Online </physloc>
            <unittitle>Helen Aminoff and David Aminoff,  [ddc001316]</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="2013">2013</unitdate><physdesc>
              <physfacet>.WAV, .PDF, and .ZIP files</physfacet>
            </physdesc>
            <dao href="http://hdl.handle.net/2027.42/113243" show="new" actuate="onRequest" ref="/repositories/2/digital_objects/131">
              <daodesc>
                <p>[view item]</p>
              </daodesc>
            </dao>
          </did>
          <odd>
            <p>(Helen Aminoff (Spouse) is interviewed by David Aminoff (Spouse) on 4/21/2009 at 3:00:00 PM in Ann Arbor, MI. David Aminoff (87) and Helen Aminoff (78) discuss living in Ann Arbor, MI and discuss the founding and evolution of the Beth Israel Congregation. Interview log: 1:00 David on coming to Ann Arbor to continue his research at the University of Michigan. Helen on meeting and marrying David. 9:10 On the makeup of the Jewish community in Ann Arbor, MI - the difference between town and gown. 13:30 The split between Beth Israel and the reform congregation Beth Emeth. 24:00 Helen on working full-time at the congregation. The growth of the congregation and moving to a new building in 1978. 47:00 On their hopes for the congregation as it moves on into the future.)</p>
          </odd>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <physloc>Online </physloc>
            <unittitle>Harlene Appelman and Henry Appelman,  [ddc001303]</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="2013">2013</unitdate><physdesc>
              <physfacet>.WAV, .PDF, and .ZIP files</physfacet>
            </physdesc>
            <dao href="http://hdl.handle.net/2027.42/113248" show="new" actuate="onRequest" ref="/repositories/2/digital_objects/132">
              <daodesc>
                <p>[view item]</p>
              </daodesc>
            </dao>
          </did>
          <odd>
            <p>(Henry Appelman (husband) is interviewed by Harlene Appelman (wife) on 4/20/2009 at 9:00:00 AM in Ann Arbor, MI. Harlene (65) interviews her husband Henry (78) about his involvement in the Jewish community in Ann Arbor and how it has changed over the years. Interview log: 1:30 Henry came to Ann Arbor in 1954 as an Associate Professor at the University of Michigan. He became part of the United Jewish Appeal. 4:50 Henry talks about Jewish Newspapers- his family was involved in the Detroit and Milwaukee Jewish News. 9:00 In the 1980s- there were more activities and opportunities to be involved in the Jewish community. Henry remembers art auction fundraisers. 16:00 Henry talks about his faith-while he doesn't necessarily believe in God- he thinks there is a responsibility to be involved in the community. 19:00 Henry and Harlene talk about Jewish sporting events for youth. 25:25 Henry remembers the Yom Kippur war in the 1970s. 27:20 Henry talks about being a Jewish faculty member at the University of Michigan and how things have changed for the community at the University over 45 years. 30:30 Henry is still active in the community. They discuss the Salon for the Jewish Federation that brings together 30something professionals. 25:00 Henry remembers the founders- the greats of the community who went fundraising years ago. 36:59 Henry talks about how Gerda Seligson ran a community with representatives from the Jewish and Gentile faiths. 38:25 Henry wants his children to be active in the community. He's very proud.)</p>
          </odd>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <physloc>Online </physloc>
            <unittitle>Zevi Bareket and Itzik Henig,  [ddc001308]</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="2013">2013</unitdate><physdesc>
              <physfacet>.WAV, .PDF, and .ZIP files</physfacet>
            </physdesc>
            <dao href="http://hdl.handle.net/2027.42/113253" show="new" actuate="onRequest" ref="/repositories/2/digital_objects/133">
              <daodesc>
                <p>[view item]</p>
              </daodesc>
            </dao>
          </did>
          <odd>
            <p>(Zevi Bareket (friend) is interviewed by Itzik Henig (friend) on 4/20/2009 at 2:00:00 PM in Ann Arbor, MI, MI. Zevi Bareket (57) and Itzik Henig (58) discuss engineering, Judaism and the development of personal awareness.  Interview log: 1:00 Zevi and Itzik on moving to the United States to work in the automobile industry. 9:00 Itzik on not judging/ measuring people based on groups but on the individuality of each person. 19:00 On the combination of nature and nurture. Itzik on his father's story as a holocaust survivor and finding proof of his family's existence. 29:15 Itzik on using awareness as a tool for change. 37:00 On the influence of different spiritual practices and Judaism.)</p>
          </odd>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <physloc>Online </physloc>
            <unittitle>Jeffrey Bernstein and Caroline Helton,  [ddc001306]</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="2013">2013</unitdate><physdesc>
              <physfacet>.WAV, .PDF, and .ZIP files</physfacet>
            </physdesc>
            <dao href="http://hdl.handle.net/2027.42/113251" show="new" actuate="onRequest" ref="/repositories/2/digital_objects/134">
              <daodesc>
                <p>[view item]</p>
              </daodesc>
            </dao>
          </did>
          <odd>
            <p>(Caroline Helton (friend) is interviewed by Jeffrey Bernstein (friend) on 4/20/2009 at 12:00:00 PM in Ann Arbor, MI. Jeffrey Bernstein and Caroline Helton (49) speak on the Beth Israel Congregation and the Jewish community of Ann Arbor, MI. Interview log: 1:00 Caroline on first moving to Ann Arbor, MI. Jeff on moving to Ann Arbor, MI with his wife. 12:40 Caroline on the support she received from the Jewish community while pregnant. 21:50 On being part of the Congregation and its relationship to being Jewish. It's worth being involved. 32:30 On the community helping each other during shivas and other religious celebrations.)</p>
          </odd>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <physloc>Online </physloc>
            <unittitle>Michael Brooks and Carol Amster,  [ddc001311]</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="2013">2013</unitdate><physdesc>
              <physfacet>.WAV, .PDF, and .ZIP files</physfacet>
            </physdesc>
            <dao href="http://hdl.handle.net/2027.42/113238" show="new" actuate="onRequest" ref="/repositories/2/digital_objects/135">
              <daodesc>
                <p>[view item]</p>
              </daodesc>
            </dao>
          </did>
          <odd>
            <p>(Carol Amster is interviewed by Michael Brooks on 4/21/2009 at 9:00:00 AM in Ann Arbor, MI. Michael talks to his friend Carol (78) about the development of the Jewish community in Ann Arbor and working together at Hillel. Interview log: 1:00 Carol and Michael talk about meeting while working at Hillel at the University of Michigan. 9:30 Carol talks about moving to Ann Arbor in the 1960s- She remembers that there was one chinese restaurant and one place to get bagels (Ralph's). 13:30 Carol remembers the first time she celebrated high holidays in Ann Arbor. She moved to Jackson for ten years and found her passion for Judaism- worked for United Jewish Appeal. 17:17 Michael remembers deciding whether to move to Ann Arbor or Boston. 20:23 Carol talks about the development of Temple Beth Emeth. It was controversial at the time because Beth Israel was conservative. 29:30 Carol talks about assimilating in Ann Arbor-it's inclusive. 36:40 Carol and Michael remember Herb- Carol's husband. He was a leader and mentor.)</p>
          </odd>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <physloc>Online </physloc>
            <unittitle>Bob Faber and Abe Ingber,  [ddc001319]</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="2013">2013</unitdate><physdesc>
              <physfacet>.WAV, .PDF, and .ZIP files</physfacet>
            </physdesc>
            <dao href="http://hdl.handle.net/2027.42/113246" show="new" actuate="onRequest" ref="/repositories/2/digital_objects/136">
              <daodesc>
                <p>[view item]</p>
              </daodesc>
            </dao>
          </did>
          <odd>
            <p>(Abe Ingber is interviewed by Bob Faber on 4/22/2009 at 2:00:00 PM in Ann Arbor, MI. Bob (86) talked with his friend Abe (90) about Jewish life in Ann Arbor, facing anti-semitism, and the state of the world today. Interview log: 2:15 Bob talks about coming to Ann Arbor from New Jersey with his wife Eunice. His baby was born just before he opened his fabric store. 5:15 Abe's family was active in Beth Israel. 9:40 Bob and Abe talk about experiencing and witnessing anti-semitism. 23:00 Abe talks about how he believes anti-semitism has not declined around the world over the years. 26:30 Bob is optimistic about the future, but Abe worries about his grandchildren. 29:00 Bob talks about his wife Eunice who recently passed away- she was a good, caring person. 31:30 Bob and Abe talk about Mollie-Abe's wife.)</p>
          </odd>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <physloc>Online </physloc>
            <unittitle>Sheila (Happy) Feigelson and Ruth Siegel,  [ddc001315]</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="2013">2013</unitdate><physdesc>
              <physfacet>.WAV, .PDF, and .ZIP files</physfacet>
            </physdesc>
            <dao href="http://hdl.handle.net/2027.42/113242" show="new" actuate="onRequest" ref="/repositories/2/digital_objects/137">
              <daodesc>
                <p>[view item]</p>
              </daodesc>
            </dao>
          </did>
          <odd>
            <p>(Ruth Siegel is interviewed by Sheila Feigelson on 4/21/2009 at 2:00:00 PM in Ann Arbor, MI. Ruth (89) talks to her friend Happy (73) about marrying into a Jewish family and the Jewish community in Ann Arbor. Interview log: 3:00 Ruth talks about moving to Ann Arbor in 1949- worked at the U of M in the music department. She lived in a boarding house with other girls. 4:45 Happy came from Minneapolis and raised family in Ann Arbor. 7:25 Happy talks about learning Hebrew. 10:00 Happy talks about what she loves about Ann Arbor-opportunities to learn. 11:00 Ruth talks about joining Rabbi White's temple- he was Conservative. Temple Beth Emeth was formed for Reform Jews. 12:40 Happy talks about singing in the Temple Beth Emeth choir. 15:50 Ruth and Happy talk about religious tolerance in Ann Arbor. 18:45 Ruth talks about her husband who worked for the Department of Defense. It was shocking when he died. People at the synagogue were supportive. Ruth talks about her sons. 29:20 Ruth and Happy talk about raising their children in Ann Arbor. 34:00 Ruth talks about converting to Judaism for her husband. They knew it would be easier to adopt children if they came from the same religion.)</p>
          </odd>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <physloc>Online </physloc>
            <unittitle>Beverly Gershowitz and Arthur Gershowitz,  [ddc001309]</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="2013">2013</unitdate><physdesc>
              <physfacet>.WAV, .PDF, and .ZIP files</physfacet>
            </physdesc>
            <dao href="http://hdl.handle.net/2027.42/113254" show="new" actuate="onRequest" ref="/repositories/2/digital_objects/138">
              <daodesc>
                <p>[view item]</p>
              </daodesc>
            </dao>
          </did>
          <odd>
            <p>(Beverly  Gershowitz (mother) is interviewed by Arthur Gershowitz (son) on 4/20/2009 at 3:00:00 PM in Ann Arbor, MI. Art (56) interviews his mother Beverly (82) about moving from New York City to the midwest. They also discuss Jewish life in Ann Arbor. Interview log: 1:20 Beverly talks about being in Michigan in the 1950s- very few Jewish people. She transitioned from Jewish life in NYC to Ann Arbor. 5:25 Beverly talks about her best friend Margo and being involved in Hadassah- Jewish organization for young women. 7:30 Art talks about growing up as a Jewish kid in Ann Arbor- only Jewish child in his class. 10:15 Bev remembers her daughter Susan marrying Sheldon- big wedding in the community. 12:10 Art remembers Sundays- Sunday school, bagels from the market. He remembers a story about stealing sodas from a vending machine at Sunday school. 13:40 Art remembers high holidays with his father. 16:00 Bev and Art remember Bev's husband, Henry. Art talks about meeting his wife because of him. 21:20 Emily's Saturday morning Bat Mitzvah. Women used to have smaller role in the community. 23:15 Bev remembers moving to Ann Arbor and her kids looking out the window. She cried. 30:10 Bev remembers not feeling welcome at first in Ann Arbor. 32:15 Bev remembers answering phones at the neighborhood store to make money as a kid in the 1930s. 39:45 Art and Bev talk about the future.)</p>
          </odd>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <physloc>Online </physloc>
            <unittitle>Zvi Gitelman and Marlene Gitelman,  [ddc001310]</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="2013">2013</unitdate><physdesc>
              <physfacet>.WAV, .PDF, and .ZIP files</physfacet>
            </physdesc>
            <dao href="http://hdl.handle.net/2027.42/113255" show="new" actuate="onRequest" ref="/repositories/2/digital_objects/139">
              <daodesc>
                <p>[view item]</p>
              </daodesc>
            </dao>
          </did>
          <odd>
            <p>(Zvi Gitelman (husband) is interviewed by Marlene Gitelman (wife) on 4/21/2009 at 8:00:00 AM in Ann Arbor, MI. Zvi Gitelman (72) and Marlene Gitelman (66) speak about their life together in Ann Arbor and being involved in the Jewish community. Interview log: 1:00 Zvi on moving to Ann Arbor from New York to be a professor. On his parents arriving in New York from the Middle East. 9:45 Marlene on the founding of the Hebrew Day School in Ann Arbor, MI. On wanting the next generation to receive the same education they received. 16:20 Zvi on being a Jewish faculty member at the University of Michigan. 26:00 On the changes undergone in Ann Arbor, MI. 34:00 Best aspects of current life.)</p>
          </odd>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <physloc>Online </physloc>
            <unittitle>Daryl M. Hafter, Monroe I. Hafter, and Robert A. Green [ddc001317]</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="2013">2013</unitdate><physdesc>
              <physfacet>.WAV, .PDF, and .ZIP files</physfacet>
            </physdesc>
            <dao href="http://hdl.handle.net/2027.42/113244" show="new" actuate="onRequest" ref="/repositories/2/digital_objects/140">
              <daodesc>
                <p>[view item]</p>
              </daodesc>
            </dao>
          </did>
          <odd>
            <p>(Daryl M. and Monroe L. Hafter is interviewed by Robert A Green on 4/22/2009 at 12:00:00 PM in Ann Arbor, MI. Robert (87) talks to his friend Daryl (78) and her husband Monroe (86) about Jewish life in Ann Arbor over the years. Interview log: 1:45 Monroe was brought up in New Jersey, drafted in the Navy, went to Harvard. 7:00 Bob came to Michigan in 1958. He remembers looking for Jewish community in Ann Arbor. 9:45 Monroe talks about how small the Jewish community was in Ann Arbor when he arrived.  10:50 Bob jokes about the president of U of M not being old enough to be president of the congregation. 14:15 Bob and Monroe talk about town Jews vs. university Jews and how they didn't mix. 16:20 Daryl talks about having Jewish children in Ann Arbor. 17:15 Burns Park Grade School- Bob remembers a teacher who took a Christmas tree cutout away from his child. 18:45 Bob tells an anecdote about Rabbi Doberson's father. Mary and Bill always sat in the same place and found someone sitting there. I'm Rabbi Doberson's father! Well this is my seat! 20:50 Bob says he enjoyed listening to Monroe speak in church. 24:00 Bob talks about anti-Israel picketers at Beth Israel. 31:00 Bob talks about Naomi- Monroe and Daryl's daughter. Daryl tells a story about Naomi selling lollipops. 35:00 Bob talks about his children.)</p>
          </odd>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <physloc>Online </physloc>
            <unittitle>Eileen D. Hymans and Saul H. Hymans,  [ddc001318]</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="2013">2013</unitdate><physdesc>
              <physfacet>.WAV, .PDF, and .ZIP files</physfacet>
            </physdesc>
            <dao href="http://hdl.handle.net/2027.42/113245" show="new" actuate="onRequest" ref="/repositories/2/digital_objects/141">
              <daodesc>
                <p>[view item]</p>
              </daodesc>
            </dao>
          </did>
          <odd>
            <p>(Eileen D. Hymans (Spouse) is interviewed by Saul Hymans (Spouse) on 4/22/2009 at 1:00:00 PM in Ann Arbor, MI. Eileen Hymans (75) and Saul Hymans (75) remember when they first met, talk about living in Ann Arbor, MI and discuss their experience within the Jewish community. Interview log: 1:00 Saul on the 100 years of Beth Israel. On being part of Beth Israel for 50 years. 11:50 On when the two met, being 18 years old. On a train ride from New York to Boston. Saul met Eileen's next door neighbor and was introduced to Eileen. 21:00 On moving to California. 30:30 On losing oen of their sons. 35:00 On raising children and maintaining the customs of the Jewish Community.)</p>
          </odd>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <physloc>Online </physloc>
            <unittitle>Jim Keen and Bonnie Keen,  [ddc001307]</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="2013">2013</unitdate><physdesc>
              <physfacet>.WAV, .PDF, and .ZIP files</physfacet>
            </physdesc>
            <dao href="http://hdl.handle.net/2027.42/113252" show="new" actuate="onRequest" ref="/repositories/2/digital_objects/142">
              <daodesc>
                <p>[view item]</p>
              </daodesc>
            </dao>
          </did>
          <odd>
            <p>(Jim Keen (husband) is interviewed by Bonnie Keen (wife) on 4/20/2009 at 1:00:00 PM in Ann Arbor, MI. Jim (46) talks with his wife Bonnie (45) about their interfaith marriage and raising two Jewish daughters. Interview log: 1:45 Jim remembers meeting Bonnie in college- he was Protestant and she was Jewish. He remembers asking her out and going to the movies. 5:15 Bonnie remembers when she first saw Jim- he was tall and cute. 6:00 Jim talks about planning to marry after college- Bonnie always planned to marry a Jewish man. They compromised- she stayed in Ann Arbor for Jim and Jim agreed to raise the girls Jewish. 8:40 Jim and Bonnie talk about their daughters' education at the Jewish Community Center. 11:30 Jim tells a story about his daughter asking What is God? and trying to decide the best way to answer that would satisfy his faith and his wife's religion. He said God is everywhere and God is good 15:45 Bonnie talks about baby naming ceremonies in the Jewish faith. 18:00 Jim remembers building a sukkah. 18:40 Jim and Bonnie talk about the Jewish community in Ann Arbor. 20:20 Jim never pictured life after college- he never would have guessed he would be raising two Jewish girls. 26:15 Jim talks about raising children Jewish while he is Christian. 27:20 Jim and Bonnie talk about how open-minded Ann Arbor is to inter-faith relationships. 28:30 Jim talks about his decision not to convert- he still feels Protestant. 30:34 Jim talks about being a non-jew in the Jewish community. 34:40 Jim and Bonnie describe each other. 36:45 Jim talks about their teenage daughters Gabby and Molly and Bonnie talks about how their interfaith marriage has impacted them. They are open-minded.)</p>
          </odd>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <physloc>Online </physloc>
            <unittitle>Diana Khiterer and Angela Keselman,  [ddc001312]</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="2013">2013</unitdate><physdesc>
              <physfacet>.WAV, .PDF, and .ZIP files</physfacet>
            </physdesc>
            <dao href="http://hdl.handle.net/2027.42/113239" show="new" actuate="onRequest" ref="/repositories/2/digital_objects/143">
              <daodesc>
                <p>[view item]</p>
              </daodesc>
            </dao>
          </did>
          <odd>
            <p>(Diana Kiterer (friend) is interviewed by Angela Keselman (friend) on 4/21/2009 at 10:00:00 AM in Ann Arbor, MI. Angela Keselman (64) and cousin Diana Khiterer (60) speak about moving to the United States from Ukraine and the differences between the two cultures. Interview log: 1:00 Angela on coming to the United States from Kiev, Ukraine. On the community of Kiev and anti-semitism. 11:00 Changes in moving to the United States from Ukraine. 16:00 On Angela's children's careers in the United States. On the possibilities in the United States and the ability to pursue dreams. 34:00 On what they are most proud of. On being proud of being Jewish.)</p>
          </odd>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <physloc>Online </physloc>
            <unittitle>Barry Margolis and Judith Lax,  [ddc001313]</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="2013">2013</unitdate><physdesc>
              <physfacet>.WAV, .PDF, and .ZIP files</physfacet>
            </physdesc>
            <dao href="http://hdl.handle.net/2027.42/113240" show="new" actuate="onRequest" ref="/repositories/2/digital_objects/144">
              <daodesc>
                <p>[view item]</p>
              </daodesc>
            </dao>
          </did>
          <odd>
            <p>(Barry Margolis is interviewed by Judith Lax on 4/21/2009 at 12:00:00 PM in Ann Arbor, MI. Barry (57) talks to his friend Judie (69) about the development of the Jewish community in Ann Arbor over the years. Interview log: 1:00 Barry's father first came to Ann Arbor in 1926. He was in farming. Barry was born in 1955. 6:20 Judie moved to Ann Arbor with her husband in the 1960s. 8:40 Barry talks about how his mother was involved in the Jewish community. Barry married his wife in the 1980s. 10:45 Barry talks about the controversial development of Temple Beth Emeth in the 1960s. 12:50 Judie talks about how the community has grown. Her son grew up as the only Jewish child in his class. 14:50 Judie tells a story about learning not to shake hands with an orthodox Jewish person. 18:30 Judie talks about her family and Jewish education in Ann Arbor. 21:25 Barry talks about his children. 25:45 Judie talks about how her father wanted a Bar Mitzvah in his 70s but passed away. 31:22 Judie talks about her work with the Jewish Community Foundation. 33:13 Barry tells a story about Osias Zwerdling. He remembers going to his house and thinking he was passed out, but he was laying on the floor counting money. 36:25 Barry talks about the important figures in the Jewish community when he was growing up.)</p>
          </odd>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <physloc>Online </physloc>
            <unittitle>Betsy Yvonne Mark and Malverne Reinhart,  [ddc01320]</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="2013">2013</unitdate><physdesc>
              <physfacet>.WAV, .PDF, and .ZIP files</physfacet>
            </physdesc>
            <dao href="http://hdl.handle.net/2027.42/113247" show="new" actuate="onRequest" ref="/repositories/2/digital_objects/145">
              <daodesc>
                <p>[view item]</p>
              </daodesc>
            </dao>
          </did>
          <odd>
            <p>(Betsy Yvonne Mark (friend) is interviewed by Malverne Reinhart (friend) on 4/22/2009 at 3:00:00 PM in Ann Arbor, MI. Betsy Mark (65) and Malverne Reinhart (82) discuss their Jewish background and relationship to Ann Arbor's Temple Beth Emeth. Interview log: 1:00 Malverne on first coming to Ann Arbor, MI a student. Betsy was also a student when she first moved to Ann Arbor. 9:00 On being Jewish and also being a school teacher. Discussion of Jewish Holidays. 14:00 On being openly Jewish and proud of the Jewish History. On the evolution of Jewish celebrations in Ann Arbor. 21:00 Betsy on joining Temple Beth Emeth. 30:00 On support received from both Beth Israel and Beth Emeth.)</p>
          </odd>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <physloc>Online </physloc>
            <unittitle>Charles Newman and Sharon Newman,  [ddc001314]</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="2013">2013</unitdate><physdesc>
              <physfacet>.WAV, .PDF, and .ZIP files</physfacet>
            </physdesc>
            <dao href="http://hdl.handle.net/2027.42/113241" show="new" actuate="onRequest" ref="/repositories/2/digital_objects/146">
              <daodesc>
                <p>[view item]</p>
              </daodesc>
            </dao>
          </did>
          <odd>
            <p>(Charles Newman (husband) is interviewed by Sharon Newman (wife) on 4/21/2009 at 1:00:00 PM in Ann Arbor, MI. Charles Newman (72) and Sharon Newman (69) discuss their time together in Ann Arbor and their involvement in the Jewish community. Interview log: 1:00 Sharon on growing up in Detroit and always being part of the Jewish Community. On joining Temple Beth Emeth. Charles speaks on his background. 9:25 Charles on a mission trip to Israel. On the Jewish community in Ann Arbor, MI and the larger United States. 16:20 Charles on a few instances of anti-semitism. On the protesting of the Russian Orchestras' performance at the University of Michigan. 23:00 Professional career as a businessman and entrepreneur. On Recellular the first company to recycle cellphones - collected over 150 million phones. 35:00 On their children.)</p>
          </odd>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <physloc>Online </physloc>
            <unittitle>Ronald Sussman, Elana Sussman, and Mira Sussman,  [ddc001304]</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="2013">2013</unitdate><physdesc>
              <physfacet>.WAV, .PDF, and .ZIP files</physfacet>
            </physdesc>
            <dao href="http://hdl.handle.net/2027.42/113249" show="new" actuate="onRequest" ref="/repositories/2/digital_objects/147">
              <daodesc>
                <p>[view item]</p>
              </daodesc>
            </dao>
          </did>
          <odd>
            <p>(Ronald (father) and Elana (mother) Sussman  is interviewed by Mira Sussman (daughter) on 4/20/2009 at 10:00:00 AM in Ann Arbor, MI. Ronald Sussman (64), Elana Sussman (65) and Mira Sussman (36) speak about being involved in the Jewish community in Ann Arbor, Michigan and the legacy they hope to leave behind. Interview log: :50 Ronald on why the family moved to Ann Arbor, MI. Elana (Lonnie) on coming to Ann Arbor, MI by accident. 11:00 On Ann Arbor as a small town. Mira on Jewish Ann Arbor as opposed to Jewish Los Angeles. 22:50 Ronald on receiving his early religious training from Holocaust survivors. 27:45 Mira on Ann Arbor being a window into many worlds. 33:30 Elana and Ronald on being a bridge generation. Mira on her hopes for her children being educated to make their own decisions on spirituality and life as a whole.)</p>
          </odd>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <physloc>Online </physloc>
            <unittitle>Israel Woronoff and Marilyn Gallatin,  [ddc001305]</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="2013">2013</unitdate><physdesc>
              <physfacet>.WAV, .PDF, and .ZIP files</physfacet>
            </physdesc>
            <dao href="http://hdl.handle.net/2027.42/113250" show="new" actuate="onRequest" ref="/repositories/2/digital_objects/148">
              <daodesc>
                <p>[view item]</p>
              </daodesc>
            </dao>
          </did>
          <odd>
            <p>(Israel Woronoff (friend) is interviewed by Marilyn  Gallatin (friend) on 4/20/2009 at 11:00:00 AM in Ann Arbor, MI. Israel (86) and Marilyn (96) talk about their lives as part of the Jewish community in Ann Arbor, anti-semitism they witnessed, and life today. Interview log: :50 Marilyn talks about coming to Ann Arbor for the University of Michigan in 1953- she was a single mother of two daughters. 6:35 Israel talks about coming to the University of Michigan after returning home from WWII. 7:30 Israel remembers meeting his wife, Faye, at Hillel. 13:00 Marilyn talks about following the Jewish faith because her parents were Jewish. It's a privilege to be a Jew. 14:25 Marilyn talks about becoming a single mother after her first husband left. 17:12 Israel talks about meeting Marilyn- he was working in a school where she was registering her children. 18:12 Israel talks about how Faye was active in the Jewish community and how Marilyn's husband was also active. 23:20 Israel asks Faye about experience anti-semitism. Faye remembers being bullied at school. 24:30 Israel remembers his brother being rejected from medical school because he was Jewish. 25:40 Israel remembers anti-semitism in the army during WWII. He tells a story about a southern officer who spoke to him in private and told him I'm Jewish too. He asked Israel to report the anti-semitic soldiers and the officer took care of it. Israel was shocked that the officer was Jewish. 33:40 Marilyn remembers being refused rental property because they wouldn't rent to Jewish people. 37:40 Israel and Marilyn talk about what their most proud of. Israel says his students and patients- Marilyn says she was always smart. 39:45 Marilyn advises her children and grandchildren to make the most out of life.)</p>
          </odd>
        </c02>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Transcripts</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>The Transcripts series (0.2 linear feet) includes paper versions of the transcripts produced by the Beth Israel Congregation.</p>
        </scopecontent>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <container type="box" label="Box [8259272460975588767]">1</container>
            <unittitle>Helen Aminoff and David Aminoff</unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <container type="box" label="Box [8259272460975588767]">1</container>
            <unittitle>Harlene Appelman and Henry Appelman</unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <container type="box" label="Box [8259272460975588767]">1</container>
            <unittitle>Zevi Bareket and Itzik Henig</unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <container type="box" label="Box [8259272460975588767]">1</container>
            <unittitle>Jeffrey Bernstein and Caroline Helton</unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <container type="box" label="Box [8259272460975588767]">1</container>
            <unittitle>Michael Brooks and Carol Amster</unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <container type="box" label="Box [8259272460975588767]">1</container>
            <unittitle>Bob Faber and Abe Ingber</unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <container type="box" label="Box [8259272460975588767]">1</container>
            <unittitle>Sheila (Happy) Feigelson and Ruth Siegel</unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <container type="box" label="Box [8259272460975588767]">1</container>
            <unittitle>Beverly Gershowitz and Arthur Gershowitz</unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <container type="box" label="Box [8259272460975588767]">1</container>
            <unittitle>Daryl M. Hafter, Monroe I. Hafter, and Robert A. Green</unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <container type="box" label="Box [8259272460975588767]">1</container>
            <unittitle>Eileen D. Hymans and Saul H. Hymans</unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <container type="box" label="Box [8259272460975588767]">1</container>
            <unittitle>Jim Keen and Bonnie Keen</unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <container type="box" label="Box [8259272460975588767]">1</container>
            <unittitle>Diana Khiterer and Angela Keselman</unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <container type="box" label="Box [8259272460975588767]">1</container>
            <unittitle>Barry Margolis and Judith Lax</unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <container type="box" label="Box [8259272460975588767]">1</container>
            <unittitle>Betsy Yvonne Mark and Malverne Reinhart</unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <container type="box" label="Box [8259272460975588767]">1</container>
            <unittitle>Charles Newman and Sharon Newman</unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <container type="box" label="Box [8259272460975588767]">1</container>
            <unittitle>Ronald Sussman, Elana Sussman, and Mira Sussman</unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <container type="box" label="Box [8259272460975588767]">1</container>
            <unittitle>Israel Woronoff and Marilyn Gallatin</unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
      </c01>
    </dsc>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
